Guide to the Isaac Hicks Papers 1791-1820 MS 297
New-York Historical Society
- Series I: Correspondence, 1791-1806; 18 Linear feet
  - Letters: 1802 A-G (Box -)
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John (1), 1802 (Box 25, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Robert & John Bolton. They request a new day book with detailed specifications. They discuss the sale and shipment of goods such as rice, tobacco, and cotton, and the payment of bills. They apologize for not replying to a number of letters, and request the creation of goods such as a milk urn and tea spoons. Ships Mentioned: Thames, Eliza
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John (2), 1802 (Box 25, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Robert & John Bolton. They primarily discuss the sale and shipment of goods, and the payment of debts. They also write of the death of Robert Bolton.
      Ships Mentioned: Columbia, Diana, General Mercer, Nixon, New York, Dodge, Ann Maria, Trial
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John (3), 1802 (Box 25, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Robert & John Bolton. A majority of the correspondence is in regard to the sale and shipment of goods and the payment of bills. One letter discusses issues with a servant woman attending the child of a client, and how her mother is against her traveling. They also request information regarding insurance policies.
      Ships Mentioned: White Oak, Diana, Eliza
    - Letters: C-E, 1802 (Box 25, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including J.A. DuBoisviolette & Co., and Thomas Ellerly. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Maryland, Darlington
    - Letters: F (Except Fisher, Samuel & Meirs; Fort, Edwin), 1802 (Box 25, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Joshua Fisher, Samuel R. Fisher, Thomas Fisher, Timothy Folger, and Edward Forbes. William Few discusses mistakes charged to his account. Joshua Fisher writes about purchasing quantities of Pepper. Samuel Fisher discusses the health of his wife and children, as well as discussing a fever and the 'health' of New York City. Edward Forbes discusses the sale and shipment of flaxseed.
    - Letters: Fisher, Samuel & Meirs, 1802 (Box 25, Folder 9)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Samuel & Meirs Fisher. They discuss mistakes in forwarding letters, the increasing number of storms, and the sale and shipment of goods. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters.
    - Letters: Fort, Edwin, 1802 (Box 25, Folder 10)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Edwin Fort. A majority of the correspondence is in regard to the payment of bills and other monetary issues.
    - Letters: G, 1802 (Box 25, Folder 11)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Samuel Gaskell. The correspondence is in regards to regular business matters such as the shipment of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Warren
  - Letters: 1802 H-P (Box -)
    - Letters: H (Except Halliday; Harvey, Deakes & Harvey; Hazard; Howland; Hussey), 1802 (Box 26, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Robert & George Hamilton, Hanna & Logan, D. Henshaw, and Hottinger & Co. Samuel Haight discusses how his daughter had dysentery. Robert & George Hamilton ask Hicks to purchase superfine flour for them, and discuss the length of voyages. Hanna & Logan discuss the markets in Liverpool. David Holmes requests money. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters such as the sale and shipment of goods, and the payment of bills.
      Ships Mentioned: Betsey, Logan, Angerania, Herkimer
    - Letters: Halliday, Alexander, 1802 (Box 26, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Alexander Halliday. Main topics include the payment of bills, the sale and shipment of goods, and other regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Resource, Sally, Eliza, Venus, Neptune, Debbe, New York
    - Letters: Harvey, Deaves & Harvey, 1802 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client, Harvey, Deaves & Harvey. Main topics include a potential breach of charter, writing on behalf of other individuals that they know, and discussing payment of bills. One letter discusses details about an agreement with the owner of the Venus.
    - Letters: Hazard; Howland, 1802 (Box 26, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Thomas Hazard, John Howland, James Howland, and Isaac Howland. Thomas Hazard discusses payment disbursements, his appreciation at the care with which his goods were handled, and his concern that goods were not shipped as he requested and his belief that Hicks did not receive the request. John Howland discusses the payment of bills, and his thoughts on Hicks charging more for completing services. James Howland discusses the payment of bills, and the purchasing of a cargo for his ship. Isaac Howland discusses the payment of bills.
      Ships Mentioned: Diana, George
    - Letters: Hussey, 1802 (Box 26, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients with the surname Hussey including David Hussey, Edward Hussey, George Hussey, Isaiah Hussey, and Peter Hussey. David Hussey discusses settling debts. Edward Hussey discusses how he is in relatively good health but his sister had recently died, and the laws surrounding purchasing a foreign vessel for the purpose of whaling. George Hussey primarily discusses regular business matters such as the shipment of goods, and also discusses the weather and how it has impacted his business.
    - Letters: J, K, L, 1802 (Box 26, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including R. Jenins, Jonathan Jones, William Kingston, and Kirk & Lukens. William Kingston writes about bringing goods to New York from Calcutta and the difficulties in doing so. Kirk & Lukens ask Hicks whether or not he would be able to sell goods from the Mediterranean (such as almond oil, parmesan cheese, paper, and silk velvet) as they are unable to sell them in Charleston. There is one letter in French. Also included are notes on some of the correspondence from an unknown modern source.
      Ships Mentioned: Exchange, Connecticut, Orient
    - Letters: M (Except Martin, Hope & Thornely; Maurice; Mellish; Moores), 1802 (Box 26, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including George McConnell, John McGowan, Machin & Macintosh, Francis Macy, Jacob Mark, John Meadery, Obed & Aaron Mitchell, Richard Mitchel & Sons, and Charles Minifie. George McConnell writes regarding his dismay at the delay of the sale of his linens. Much of the correspondence is in regard to the sale and shipment of cotton and flaxseed, and the payment of debts. Obed & Aaron Mitchell discuss a contract to provide New York with whale oil for city lights and public light houses. Included are multiple duplicates.
      Ships Mentioned: Exchange, Eliza, Neptune, Venus, Pearl, Fame, Sally
    - Letters: Martin, Hope & Thornely; Maurice, 1802 (Box 26, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Hope & Thornely Martin and Benjamin Maurice. Hope & Thornely Martin introduce themselves to Hicks and then discuss a treaty between England and France, the cotton trade, and the sale and shipment of goods like tobacco, rice, and flaxseed. Benjamin Maurice introduces himself to Hicks and then discusses procuring insurance.
      Ships Mentioned: Brothers, Ocean, Birmingham, Darlington, Washington, Dolphin, Eliza, Harlequin
    - Letters: Mellish; Moores, 1802 (Box 26, Folder 9)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including J& W Mellish and Reuben Moores. The correspondence is primarily in regards to regular business matters including travel and trade with St. Petersburg, Russia. Reuben Moores discusses his lack of goods to sell, and the weather and how it relates to his shipment of coal.
      Ships Mentioned: Liberty
    - Letters: P (Except Paddock; Prudhomme), 1802 (Box 26, Folder 10)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including John Paige, and John Potts, among others. John Paige asks Hicks to procure payments for him. Perrot & Lee discuss the sale and shipment of goods such as beef and pork, pepper, whale oil, and beeswax, among other goods. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters such as the sale and shipment of goods and the payment of bills.
      Ships Mentioned: William
    - Letters: Paddock; Prudhomme, 1802 (Box 26, Folder 11)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Judah Paddock, and L Prudhomme. Main topics include the sale and shipment of goods such as cotton and tobacco. Judah Paddock discusses attending the funeral of a colleague, and discusses how his business is now in the hands of John Haslett. He also discusses voyages that he has taken and how it has effects his business.
      Ships Mentioned: Hector, Juno
  - Letters: 1802 R-W (Box -)
    - Letters: R (Except Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan; Rodman; Rotch), 1802 (Box 27, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Abel Rawson, William Riddell, John Robinson & Sons, and Rocquette Beeldemaker & co. The correspondence is primarily in regard to regular business matters such as trade and finances.
      Ships Mentioned: Oneid
    - Letters: Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan (1), 1802 (Box 27, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan. They discuss the sale and shipment of goods such as cotton, coals, and. They also discuss the payment of bills and other financial matters. They discuss voyages their ships have made as well.
      Ships Mentioned: General Mercer, Mars, Brothers, Columbia, Diana, Anne, Allegany
    - Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan (2), 1802 (Box 27, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan. They predominantly discuss regular business matters such as the sale and shipment of goods and the payment of bills.
      Ships Mentioned: John, Samuel Elam, General Mercer, Ocean
    - Letters: Rodman; Rotch, 1802 (Box 27, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Samuel Rodman, Thomas Rotch and William Rotch. Samuel Rodman predominantly discusses payment for goods and certificates of landing, and occasionally discusses voyages that he and his ships are taking to New York. William Rotch asks when some of his debts are due and discusses other accounting matters. One letter mentions how Hicks's account of the 'gospel messengers' is acceptable.
      Ships Mentioned: Phebe, Jupiter, America
    - Letters: S (Except Smith & Ridgeway; Spear, Robert), 1802 (Box 27, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Joseph Scott, William Segel, Samuel Stoneman, and J Sullivan. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and shipment of goods. Many letters discuss voyages taken by clients. Many other letters have to do with accounting matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Sally
    - Letters: Smith & Ridgeway; Spear, Robert, 1802 (Box 27, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Smith & Ridgeway, and Robert Spear. Smith & Ridgeway discuss how one of their ships is overloaded, how the ship must be lightened, and asks what Hicks would like to do in regards to the situation. Robert Spear discusses regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Phoebe Ann
    - Letters: V-W, 1802 (Box 27, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Ruolph Vogeler, P.P. Walter, John Warder & Sons, Elijah Waring, John Watkins, Richard Wheatley, Wheeler & Warren, and Timothy Wyer. P.P Walter discusses the procurement of insurance policies, auctions, and accounting matters. John Warder & Sons discuss the sale and shipment of goods—especially goods such as flour to St. Domingo. John Warring discusses the sale of salt. Much of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and shipment of goods and other regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Warren, Triton, Friendship
  - Letters: 1803 A-Coffin (Box -)
    - Letters: A, 1803 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including William Abbott; Gideon Alden; John Alden; and Alexander, Webster, & Co. Main topics include the sale and shipment of goods such as cotton, rice, flour, and tobacco; accounting matters such as sending funds and paying bills; and other regular business matters. William Abbott writes of the arrival of three boys on the ship Milford and what should be done with them. Letters from Gideon Alden include inventory lists and accounting ledger pages. Gideon Alden also discusses the difficulty in procuring spices.
      Ships Mentioned:Milford, Diana, Warren, Olympus
    - Letters: B (Except Benson; Bolton), 1803 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Abirhai Barnard, Richard Blow, and Baddington, Philips, & Sharp. The correspondence is primarily in regard to regular business matters such as the sale and shipment of goods and accounting matters. Included are prices current on American produce
      Ships Mentioned: Prospect
    - Letters: Benson, Cropper, & Benson, 1803 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client, Benson, Cropper, & Benson—specifically William Benson. The correspondence is primarily in regards to regular business matters. In one letter, William Benson discusses his entrance into the American trade market. He includes how there are increasing hostilities between England and France, how the French army had taken control over the city of Hanover, and how trade in that region is going to be difficult if not impossible. He also discusses an increased duty on cotton imported into England.
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John (1), 1803 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, Robert & John Bolton. They discuss the changing prices of goods such as rice and cotton. They also ask Hicks to send money to individuals that it appears the Boltons owe money to. They request a new receipt book be made and sent to them. They mention the fact that the Columbia had run aground and was taking on water. They then go on to discuss the potential damages that may have happened to the goods in her hold.
      Ships Mentioned: Thames, Nixon, Columbia
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John (2), 1803 (Box 28, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, Robert & John Bolton. They discuss the changing prices of goods such as oats and bran, and request information on prices as well. They also ask Hicks to send money to individuals that it appears the Boltons owe money to and include copies of invoices.
      Ships Mentioned: Thames
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John (3), 1803 (Box 28, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, Robert & John Bolton. They request information on insurance policies, and discuss prices of goods such as spices, cotton, and tobacco. The majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters. Some letters are duplicated and triplicated between folders.
      Ships Mentioned: Thames, Ann Maria, Columbia
    - Letters: C (Except Coffin; Cropper & Benson), 1803 (Box 28, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including David Callaghan, Sam Coates, and many others. Main topics include the procurement of insurance, the sale and shipment of goods, and the payment of debts.
      Ships Mentioned: Diana, Thames
    - Letters: Coffin, 1803 (Box 28, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients with the surname Coffin, including Alex Coffin, Mark Coffin, Ann Coffin, and James Coffin. Alex Coffin discusses the political turmoil between England and France, and the embargo that has happened because of it. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters such as the shipping of goods and the payment of bills.
      Ships Mentioned: Penman, Caledonia
  - Letters: 1803 Cropper & Benson-Halliday (Box -)
    - Letters: Cropper & Benson (1), 1803 (Box 29, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, Cropper & Benson. They discuss the declining demand of flour, rice and wheat, and how therefore the prices have also been declining. They also discuss the sale of goods such as turpentine and potash. They discuss military preparations happening in France and Holland, and how additional precautions must be taken. Also included is a list of account sales of cotton for the ship Perseverance.
      Ships Mentioned: Perseverance, Olympus
    - Letters: Cropper & Benson (2), 1803 (Box 29, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, Cropper & Benson. They discuss how the French have taken control of Hamburg, and how that effects the pricing of goods. They mention the sale of earthenware and other goods. They also discuss regular business matters like accounting and the sale and shipment of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Perseverance, Warren
    - Letters: D (Except Drinker), 1803 (Box 29, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Jason Danach, William Dawson, and John Delano. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the payment of bills and other accounting matters. One letter is in French.
      Ships Mentioned: Ann, Jupiter, Fortitude
    - Letters: Drinker, 1803 (Box 29, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client, Henry Drinker. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters such as the sale and shipment of goods and the payment of bills. One letter discusses contacting Alexander Hamilton, Esq. about reporting a debt from Bowne & Pearsall "from which he might form a case & state an opinion therein". Another letter discusses their 'meeting' and complaints against members.
    - Letters: E-F (Except Fisher; Folger), 1803 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including J. Edmonds, P. Fish, and Edward Forbes. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters such as accounting and the sale and shipment of goods.
    - Letters: Fisher, 1803 (Box 29, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from clients with the surname Fisher, predominantly Joshua Fisher, and Samuel & Miers Fisher. The correspondence is primarily in regards to regular business matters like accounting and the sale and shipment of goods.
    - Letters: Folger, 1803 (Box 29, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from Benjamin Folger and Ezra Folger. The communications is primarily in regards to the payment of bills.
    - Letters: G, 1803 (Box 29, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including G. & A. Gardner, Benjamin Garnett, Samuel Gaskell, and William Gibson. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and shipment of goods and other regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Commerce, Henry
    - Letters: H (Except Halliday; Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey; Hottingen & Co.; Hussey), 1803 (Box 29, Folder 9)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Robert & George Hamilton, A. Hart, and others. Robert & George Hamilton request that Hicks ship them cargo and lists the prices they are willing to pay. A. Hart writes how his "store is now full of goods, but the owners have fled" and how he can not access their storage. J. Hart writes how a Mr. McNeil was acting foolishly and imprudently after he disembarked in London. Also included in this folder is a collection of letters from Hicks to Judah Paddock and is filed under 'H' for Hicks. Much of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and shipment of goods such as cotton and tobacco.
    - Letters: Halliday, 1803 (Box 29, Folder 10)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Alex Halliday. Halliday discusses being sent money via multiple different ships, and the shipment of goods such as cotton.
      Ships Mentioned: Thames, Ann Maria, Neptune, Eliza, Mary, Venus
  - Letters: 1803 Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey-Moores (Box -)
    - Letters: Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey, 1803 (Box 30, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey. The correspondence is in regards to regular business matters, and primarily relates to the sale and shipment of goods.
    - Letters: Hottingen; Hussey, 1803 (Box 30, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Hottingen & Co., and individuals with the surname Hussey. Hottingen & Co. discusses how they are short on funds and requests Hicks settle his account with them. They predominantly discuss accounting matters. In one letter they discuss how their ports are in a state of blockade, and how it is highly likely that all the ports surrounding them are blockaded also.
      Ships Mentioned: Warren, Federal George, Union
    - Letters: J (Except Jenkins, Jonathan and Robert), 1803 (Box 30, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Jackson & Hartstene, A & E Jarmey, and Jonathan Jones. Jackson & Hartstene discuss how they are very much in need of the goods in the order they placed, as well as goods that they have shipped to Hicks. A & E Jarmey asks Hicks to sell the flour that they are sending him.
      Ships Mentioned: Echo, Neptune
    - Letters: Jenkins, Jonathan & Robert, 1803 (Box 30, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Jonathan and Robert Jenkins. Jonathan Jenkins discusses how he has been in poor health for some time, goods Jenkins' wife has sent for Hicks' wife, and information about the voyage of the brig Betsey. Robert Jenkins discusses executing a mortgage, the changing price of staves, and other regular business matters. Also included is a letter granting Hicks power of attorney.
      Ships Mentioned: Hawk, Betsey, General Mercer
    - Letters: K (Except Kirk & Lukens), 1803 (Box 30, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Kirivan & Morrogh, and Peter Keteltas. Correspondence discusses the changing flour market, the increasing hostilities between France and Great Britain and the subsequent changes in commerce, and the procurement of insurance policies.
      Ships Mentioned: Connecticut
    - Letters: Kirk & Lukens, 1803 (Box 30, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, Kirk & Lukens. They discuss exchange rates between London and the United States and request further information regarding these rates. They discuss the evolving cotton and tobacco markets and the changing prices of goods such as rice and pork.
      Ships Mentioned: Charleston